Since 2003, a special type of scam targeting the elderly
Od roku 2003 w Japonii króluje biorące na cel osoby starsze
called the money transfer scam has proliferated in Japan.
oszustwo zwane „przekrętem na przelew”.
Financial damages increased every year, reaching 56.5 billion yen in 2014.
Straty finansowe rosną z roku na rok. W 2014 r. wynosiły 56,5 miliarda jenów.
Now, in 2019, scammers have changed their techniques,
W 2019 roku oszuści zmienili metody,
and the damage continues.
w dalszym ciągu okradając obywateli.
Hey! You screwed it up, so stop hanging around on the line!
Skopałeś, przestań się obijać!
Where's your ambition?
Gdzie twoje ambicje?
Do I have to follow the script exactly?
Muszę się trzymać scenariusza?
If you can keep the person on the line, you can say what you want.
Dopóki utrzymasz rozmówcę, rób, co chcesz.
-I got it. -Yes! Good job, you little punk!
- Mam. - Dobra robota, gnojku!
You all are very precious to me.
Bardzo was cenię.
I didn't think you'd become professional players so quickly.
Nie sądziłem, że tak szybko opanujecie tę sztukę.
I'm really impressed.
Jestem pod wrażeniem.
Excuse me.
Przepraszam.
Oh, Kanbe.
Kanbe.
Sorry for calling suddenly.
Wybacz, że tak nagle cię wezwałem.
You've been doing very well recently.
Masz wspaniałe wyniki.
Don't just stand there, come sit down.
Nie stój tak, usiądź.
Yes. Thank you.
Oczywiście. Dziękuję.
Excuse me.
Przepraszam.
I hear you've done well for your age.
Dobrze sobie radzisz jak na swój wiek.
Go ahead. Have a drink.
Śmiało, napij się.
Come on, have another!
Jeszcze raz!
Have some food, too.
Zjedz coś.
Thank you.
Dziękuję.
Good-for-nothing scam artist.
Bezużyteczny oszust.
We never would have let a sneaky bastard like this
Kiedyś nie pozwolilibyśmy, żeby takie ścierwo
sit at our table in the old days.
zasiadało przy naszym stole.
None of that, now.
Wystarczy.
The type of youth the Yakuza need
Yakuza potrzebuje młodych ludzi,
are men who can fight for us and men who can make us money.
którzy mogą dla nas walczyć albo zarabiać pieniądze.
We need to take care of people like Kanbe.
Tacy jak Kanbe są dla nas cenni.
Have another drink.
Napij się.
-Have some meat, too. -Thank you.
- Skosztuj mięsa. - Dziękuję.
-By the way, Kanbe... -Yes?
- Przy okazji... - Tak?
How many stores are you running now?
Ile oddziałów prowadzisz?
Three.
Trzy.
I'd like you to add six more within half a year.
W ciągu pół roku otworzysz kolejne sześć.
Six? In addition to the three I have now?
Poza tymi trzema?
Impossible for this little brat.
Gówniarz jest bez szans.
No use giving him a bunch of money he'll just lose.
Szkoda marnować na niego forsę.
I'll consult with...
Skonsultuję to z...
my store managers, then.
kierownikami.
Can you add another six or not?
Otworzysz kolejne sześć?
Yes, I can.
Tak.
Good to hear.
Wspaniale.
Okay!
Doskonale!
Eat up! Keep eating!
Masz zjeść wszystko!
Kanbe-san, are you okay?
Wszystko w porządku, panie Kanbe?
I'll get you something to drink!
Przyniosę coś do picia.
Dokugawa!
Dokugawa!
I'm fine.
Nic mi nie jest.
Our financiers said that soon
Doradcy mówią, że wkrótce
they'll have a new register and a large amount of burner phones.
będą mieli nowy rejestr i sporo nowych telefonów na kartę.
So they want to take this opportunity to make some money. Is that the deal?
Chcą wykorzystać okazję i zarobić. O to chodzi?
Yeah, that's right.
Tak.
But that's a total of nine stores.
To łącznie dziewięć oddziałów.
We don't have enough players or managers.
Nie mamy tylu pracowników ani kierowników.
Dokugawa.
Dokugawa.
Can you take over the new stores?
Przejmiesz nowe oddziały?
I will if I have to, but...
Jeśli będzie trzeba, ale...
What will we do with our current store?
co z pozostałymi?
Out of the five of them, who could be the manager?
Kto z tej piątki może zostać kierownikiem?
Well...
Cóż.
Choosing out of those five, it would have to be...
Gdybym miał wybierać...
I'm the manager?
Zostałem kierownikiem?
-You want me to be the manager? -Yep.
- Mam kierować? - Tak.
We have to open six more stores.
Otwieramy sześć oddziałów.
EPISODE 4
ODCINEK 4
With training and everything, I won't have the time to be here.
Nie będę miał czasu tu bywać przez szkolenia i resztę.
-But I don't have any experience, and-- -Don't be a coward!
Przecież...
There are no offers here. Only orders.
To nie propozycja, tylko rozkaz.
You have no choice.
Nie masz wyjścia.
This is a virgin register.
Oto nowy rejestr.
"Virgin register"?
Nowy?
Completely new data that has never been used by scammers before.
Zupełnie nowe dane. Tych ludzi nikt jeszcze nie ściemniał.
And on top of that, it's all been checked out.
Wszystko sprawdzone.
This is a secret weapon that register compilers rarely give out.
To tajna broń, której wyłudzacze danych pilnują.
There are 400 names in total.
Mamy tam 400 nazwisk.
Your profits for the month need to reach at least 120 million yen.
Macie w tym miesiącu zarobić co najmniej 120 milionów jenów.
120 million?
Aż 120 milionów?
Do your best! Don't disappoint Kanbe-san,
Postarajcie się! Nie zawiedź pana Kanbego,
Mr. Manager.
kierowniku.
-Mr. Manager. -Congrats.
- Kierownik. - Gratulacje.
Good luck.
Powodzenia.
Made it! I made it.
Zdążyłem!
Hey, Kusano.
Hej, Kusano.
Do you have time?
Masz chwilę?
-Cheers. -Cheers!
- Zdrowie.
Congratulations.
Gratuluję.
Stop it.
Przestań.
I'm freaking out right now.
Stresuję się tym.
Don't worry, you're a natural!
Masz wrodzony talent!
I knew it from the beginning!
Od razu to wiedziałem!
I don't know...
No nie wiem...
You are. I know you are.
Wiem, że to prawda.
I've been sure of it all along.
Cały czas to wiedziałem.
I wonder if I can be like Kanbe-san.
Ciekawe, czy mogę być jak pan Kanbe.
Kanbe-san?
Pan Kanbe?
He's amazing.
Jest niesamowity.
He's so cool.
Świetny.
I did that training because apparently there was someone who saw promise in me.
Wziąłem udział w szkoleniu, bo ktoś dostrzegł we mnie potencjał.
No way! Was it Dokugawa-san?
No co ty! Dokugawa?
No, apparently not.
Raczej nie.
So...
Zatem...
I think it might be Kanbe-san.
To mógł być pan Kanbe.
That's amazing! You're a real life prodigy!
Niesamowite! Jesteś geniuszem!
A genius scammer... The greatest scam artist!
Oszust i geniusz. Guru przekręciarzy!
What I'm saying is, I really want to do my best as manager.
Jako kierownik dam z siebie wszystko.
Great. And you can do it! I know you can do it, Kusano!
Świetnie. Poradzisz sobie!
Hey, let's exchange numbers.
Wymieńmy się numerami.
What? We can't!
Nie wolno nam.
We shouldn't even be drinking together!
Nie powinniśmy nawet razem pić.
It's just for emergencies! We have to help each other.
Na wszelki wypadek. Trzeba sobie pomagać.
I'm the manager now, I have to follow the rules.
Jako kierownik muszę przestrzegać zasad.
I'm telling you it's fine!
To nic takiego!
Kanbe-san has Dokugawa-san, right?
Pan Kanbe ma Dokugawę, nie?
We're like that!
Też będziemy takim duetem.
If something happens, I'll do whatever you need me to do.
W razie czego zrobię, co każesz.
Okay? Partner?
Wspólnicy?
Our new manager!
Nasz nowy kierownik!
Excuse me.
Przepraszam.
Manager.
Kierownik.
-Here. -Thanks.
- Trzymaj. - Dzięki.
0-9-0...
Zero, dziewięć, zero...
I'm going to do my best!
Dam z siebie wszystko!
FOR INTERNAL USE ONLY
DO UŻYTKU WEWNĘTRZNEGO
I'm the manager!
Jestem kierownikiem!
You scared me!
Wystraszyłaś mnie!
Look, Misaki made some cookies. Want some?
Misaki upiekła ciasteczka.
What? I don't want any at all.
Nie, skądże.
What?
Co?
Are you okay?
Wszystko gra?
Why?
Dlaczego?
You look scary.
Strasznie wyglądasz.
No, I'm doing some really important work I've been given.
Pracuję nad ważnym projektem.
So, could you not disturb me?
Możesz mi nie przeszkadzać?
I'm not doing nearly as good.
U mnie trochę gorzej.
There aren't enough caretakers, so they want me to work more.
Mają za mało opiekunów, proszą mnie o nadgodziny.
But I also have to look after your father.
Ale muszę opiekować się tatą.
You're being sarcastic...
To sarkazm?
You want me to look after Dad more.
Mam poświęcać więcej czasu tacie.
What?
Co?
It sounded like you were complaining about me.
Będziesz mi robić wyrzuty?
I didn't say anything like that!
Nic takiego nie powiedziałam!
I'm working on something really big, so I don't have the time.
Mam ważną pracę i nie mam czasu.
I'm doing my best,
Daję z siebie wszystko,
so don't do that.
więc nie rób mi tego.
You don't have the time? For your father, you mean?
Nie masz czasu? Dla ojca?
No...
Nie...
Why are you so irritable? You're acting like a fool.
Coś ty taki drażliwy? Zachowujesz się jak idiota.
Your father has cancer!
Twój ojciec ma raka!
I know that. That's why I'm working!
Wiem, dlatego pracuję!
I talked with the doctor today
Dziś rozmawiałam z lekarzem
about the most recent test results.
o ostatnich wynikach.
And?
I co?
The cancer metastasized.
Ma przerzuty.
That means...
Czyli...
Hey. I heard you're manager now.
Cześć. Ponoć zostałeś kierownikiem.
Yeah. What about it?
I co z tego?
Good job. Sounds like you'll be making more money.
Dobra robota. Będziesz więcej zarabiał.
Let's talk about that payment issue. How about tomorrow?
Pogadajmy o tym długu. Może jutro?
About that... Can I consult with Kanbe-san or Dokugawa-san first?
Wolałbym najpierw porozmawiać z panami Kanbem lub Dokugawą.
Why?
Po co?
You're the one who introduced me, so I should let them know about this.
Wprowadziłeś mnie, więc powinni wiedzieć.
This is between you and me, not them!
To sprawa między nami!
-I wonder-- -Hey, punk!
- Zastanawiam się... - Pajacu!
I have a responsibility to report this as manager--
Jako kierownik muszę to zgłosić...
Don't get cocky!
Nie cwaniakuj!
I'm just working hard at my job.
Ja tylko ciężko pracuję.
Listen here. Are you going to give me the money or not?
Posłuchaj. Dasz mi tę forsę czy nie?
-Let me talk to my superiors. -You--
- Pomówię z przełożonymi. - Ty...
Let me talk to my superiors.
Pomówię z przełożonymi.
-You have some nerve! -I have to go now.
- Masz tupet! - Muszę kończyć.
Hey!
Koleś!
Don't hang up on me!
Nie rozłączaj mi się!
The person you dialed will not accept your call--
Osoba, do której dzwonisz, zablokowała twój numer...
Did that punk really just block me!
Frajer mnie zablokował!
I'm a member of the criminal world now.
Jestem teraz gangsterem.
These kinds of exchanges don't bother me anymore.
Jestem ponad takimi pierdołami.
Don't mess with me! Punk!
Nie zadzieraj ze mną, śmieciu!
Okay!
No dobra!
Hello. It's Takuya... What should I do?
Halo? Mówi Takuya. Co mam robić?
-What should I do? -Hello.
- Co robić? - Halo?
-It's an old man. -Hello.
- To starszy facet.
Hang up. It's a waste of time if not an old lady.
Rozłącz się. Jak to nie babka, to szkoda czasu.
Damn it!
Szlag!
This is so frustrating.
Wnerwia mnie to.
We're going to use up this virgin register in a week.
Wyczerpiemy rejestr w tydzień.
Let's try the next one.
Dzwoń pod kolejny.
Everyone.
Uwaga.
Can I have a moment?
Proszę o uwagę.
Hey, manager! What's up?
Co tam, kierowniku?
-What is it? -Here.
- Co to? - Proszę.
Here.
Trzymaj.
What is this? A script?
Co to? Scenariusz?
Yeah, I wrote it myself.
Sam go napisałem.
The setting is a son who lost important papers from his job
Przedstawiamy się jako syn, który zgubił dokumenty z pracy
and needs money to cover the loss.
i musi pokryć koszty.
You're acting like a real manager!
Wczułeś się w rolę.
After we succeed with this,
Jeśli się uda,
we can say the son caused trouble for a client and change it up.
powiemy, że syn narobił szkód klientowi.
We can go after weak targets two or three times--
Słabe cele ogolimy nawet trzykrotnie.
And have them pay as much as possible.
Wyciśniemy z nich jak najwięcej.
That's right.
Świetnie.
This is pretty detailed. What did you use as a model?
Sporo szczegółów. Na kim się wzorowałeś?
I used myself.
Na sobie.
What?
Co?
I had to do this kind of thing at my old job.
Robiłem takie coś w poprzedniej pracy.
Hey!
No nie!
We're finally hearing about Kusano's dirty past!
Mroczna przeszłość Kusana!
You said you got fired because of the Lehman collapse, but the truth is out!
Mówiłeś, że firma zbankrutowała, ale prawda wyszła na jaw!
It's not that!
To nie tak.
Hurry up and memorize that, then we practice! The clock is ticking!
Nauczcie się scenariusza i lecimy. Czas ucieka!
-Hello. -What should I do?
- Tak? - Co mam zrobić?
-Will this make it better? Really? -Hello.
- To pomoże? - Halo?
Hello. Help me!
Halo? Pomocy!
I'm in trouble! I might lose my job!
Mam kłopoty, mogę stracić pracę!
Tanaka lost an important file that contained customers' personal information.
Tanaka zgubił akta zawierające dane klienta.
At this rate, we may lose nearly 100 million yen.
Może nas to kosztować sto milionów jenów.
It'll be okay if I can give them three million today.
Wystarczy, że dam im dziś trzy miliony.
The CEO is saying, if he pays three million
Prezes mówi, że jeśli zapłaci trzy miliony
out of the 100 million that was lost, he won't fire him.
z tych stu, to go nie zwolni.
-Three million yen? -Yes, that's right.
- Trzy miliony? - Tak.
If you transfer three million to us by three p.m., your son won't lose his job.
Proszę zrobić przelew do 15, to zachowa posadę.
There's no time to lose!
Nie ma czasu do stracenia!
I'm glad to hear that! Please send the money by three o'clock today.
Całe szczęście. Proszę tylko zdążyć do 15.
Thank you.
Dziękuję.
We got it!
Mamy ją!
Yes! Down with the elderly!
Tak! Staruchy do piachu!
Down with the elderly!
Staruchy do piachu!
-Yes! -I'm going to faint!
- Tak! - Zaraz zemdleję!
Yes.
Tak?
-Mom told me to give this back. -Thanks.
- Mama kazała mi to zwrócić. - Dzięki.
Want to come in?
Wejdziesz?
Sorry, I've been tasked with some important stuff at work,
Wybacz, mam ważne zadanie z pracy.
so I'm super busy.
Mam masę roboty.
Oh...
Jasne.
Later.
Na razie.
Hello, Mako-chan!
Cześć, Mako!
-Hello. -How are you?
- Dzień dobry. - Jak leci?
Come have a cup of tea!
Wejdź na herbatkę!
-I'm sorry, I'm really busy-- -Don't say that!
- Jestem trochę zajęty... - Nie mów tak!
No, really.
Naprawdę.
What is this?
Co to?
Homework.
Praca domowa.
It smells, doesn't it?
Aż pachnie, prawda?
-Here you are. -Thanks.
- Proszę. - Dziękuję.
I heard about the test results.
Słyszałam o wynikach taty.
I'm sorry.
Przykro mi.
I just have to keep making money.
Muszę zarabiać.
I've been given a big job.
Dostałem ważną posadę.
I'm busy with that,
Zabiera mi mnóstwo czasu,
and I really feel like I can do it.
ale sobie poradzę.
Now for our next topic.
Kolejny temat.
How terrible!
Okropne!
A man in his 20s
Dwudziestoparoletni mężczyzna
was arrested on suspicion of stealing four million yen.
został aresztowany i oskarżony o kradzież czterech milionów.
The man is suspected of being a "receiver," a person who picks up money
Podejrzewa się, że pełni funkcję kuriera odbierającego pieniądze dla grup
for money transfer scam groups.
zajmujących się oszustwami.
They make calls...
Ich członkowie dzwonią...
That's so terrible.
Okropne.
...and demand a settlement to...
...i żądają ugody...
How awful. What kind of person would pick on the elderly like that?
Okropne. Jak można tak oszukiwać starszych ludzi?
Someone like me is the perfect target!
Ja byłabym idealnym celem!
That's right, the other day,
Niedawno
I bought this through mail order.
zamówiłam takie coś.
Look!
Spójrzcie.
That's...
To...
Hey, grandma...
Babciu...
I'm actually excited now.
Ale się cieszę.
I'm looking forward to when those scammers give me a call.
Niech tylko zadzwonią.
When they do, I'm going to pretend to be fooled
Udam, że się nabrałam,
and lure them here.
i ich tu ściągnę.
Yes.
Tak.
Okay. I'll be there right away.
Zaraz będę.
I'm from the law office.
Reprezentuję kancelarię.
Thank you so much.
Dziękuję.
I brought the money like we discussed.
Przyniosłam pieniądze.
Here.
Proszę.
Is my grandson all right?
Wnukowi nic nie grozi?
-How is he? -Um...
- Jak się czuje? - Cóż...
-I think we can avoid a trial... -Yes?
- Raczej unikniemy procesu. - Tak?
But we won't know for sure until we talk to the claimant.
Ale najpierw musimy porozmawiać z powodem.
Anyway... We'll do our best. We'll be in touch.
Zrobimy, co w naszej mocy. Odezwiemy się.
Thank you! Please, help him!
Dziękuję! Pomóżcie mu!
Please!
Proszę!
What are you doing?
Co robicie?
Let go!
Puśćcie!
Let go of me!
Puszczajcie!
Do you know who I work for?
Wiecie, dla kogo pracuję?
There was an attack yesterday.
Wczoraj doszło do napadu.
The collector was ambushed
Napadnięto kuriera.
and is currently in a coma.
Obecnie jest w śpiączce.
Who did this?
Kto za tym stoi?
They haven't been found yet,
Nie wiemy,
but it's definitely someone on the inside.
ale to wewnętrzna robota.
No matter how high we keep our guards up,
Możemy uważać,
there are punks on the inside who leak information.
ale zawsze jakiś kretyn coś chlapnie.
It can't be helped.
Nic nie zrobimy.
Do we go to the police?
Pójdziemy na policję?
Don't be an idiot!
Coś ty, głupi?
That would be the end of everything!
Byłoby po nas!
Oh, I see.
Rozumiem.
In scams, money you fail to make never existed from the beginning.
W tej branży nic nie zarobiliście, jeśli nie macie forsy w rękach.
You have to let it go!
Zapomnijcie o tym!
That's how we work.
Tak to wygląda.
-So we just put up with it? -Hey!
- Mamy się z tym liczyć? - Posłuchaj.
We're not the Yakuza.
Nie jesteśmy yakuzą.
We're businessmen.
To biznes.
Of course,
Oczywiście...
we won't forgive traitors.
ukarzemy zdrajców.
Your job is to not get distracted and to keep making money!
Wy macie się skupić i zarabiać forsę.
-Kusano! -Yes.
- Kusano! - Tak?
Will you reach your target?
Osiągniecie cel?
-We're trying. -That's not what I asked!
- Staramy się. - Nie o to pytam!
I asked whether you'll achieve your target!
Osiągniecie cel?
We will.
Tak.
Together.
Wspólnie.
Good.
Świetnie.
I'm trusting you.
Ufam ci.
Kazuto...
Kazuto...
Kusano.
Kusano?
Hello.
Halo?
Hey, can you talk?
Cześć, możesz gadać?
Sure.
Jasne.
I've been thinking about our strategy,
Myślałem o strategii.
and I don't think it's enough to just change the scripts.
Zmiana scenariusza to za mało.
Could we meet and talk about this in person?
Możemy to obgadać?
Yeah, sure.
Jasne.
There's a restaurant near my house,
Koło mnie jest restauracja.
let's meet there in 30 minutes.
Spotkajmy się tam za pół godziny.
Okay!
Jasne!
Great, thanks.
Dzięki.
A real meeting!
Spotkanie!
Kusano!
Kusano!
-Excuse me. -Whoa!
- Przepraszam. - Rany!
Do you know how to get to district 4?
Jak dojadę do czwartego dystryktu?
What?
Co?
Careful!
Uwaga!
What should I do?
Co robić?
Let go of me!
Puszczaj!
-I'm the manager! -Get him in!
Jestem kierownikiem!
Shut your mouth!
Stul dziób!
Kusano!
Kusano!
Put on some music, he's too loud.
Włącz muzykę, bo hałasuje.
Subtitle translation by Marti McElreath
Napisy: Konrad Szabowicz